my pleasure we appreciate that thank you
please have a seat thank you very much
thank you very much for having us happy
to do today before you decided to join
the CIA can you describe the the
Zeitgeist of this time and uh what
inspired you at that time
it's easier for me to tell you what
inspired me really it was my grandfather
I come from an immigrant family my
grandparents all four of my grandparents
came from the Greek island of Rhodes and
uh arrived here in the early 1930s
my grandfather my father's father to
hear him tell the story
you know Franklin Roosevelt was
personally waiting for him at Ellis
Island to give him citizenship and a job
and a future and um
and so he was very very patriotic uh and
very solidly Democratic he was a huge
Roosevelt supporter we even had a
picture a framed picture of Franklin
Roosevelt on our television until the
day he died and so he always
he always instilled in me this notion
that the country was so good to us when
we needed a helping hand that we needed
to give something back and so when I was
in college I really only considered
public service I didn't consider
anything else business or
private companies nothing only public
service
the Zeitgeist at the time it's funny
that you ask you know all the interviews
I've given and I've given thousands of
interviews nobody's ever asked me that
before
um
you know I'm almost a little bit ashamed
to tell you that that I sort of bought
into the whole neo-liberal
um
you know American exceptionalism USA
number one when I was in college we were
picking off little countries like
Grenada and Panama and
I don't know it just seemed
like we were a Force for good Jimmy
Carter had started the annual human
rights report in 1977 and so I thought
maybe I'll join the Foreign Service I'll
go to the state department and see the
world and I really wanted to travel and
see the world
and then in graduate school I had a
professor who
wasn't really a professor he was
he was a CIA officer undercover as a
professor and he was looking for people
who might fit into the cia's culture he
liked my writing style and so he asked
me if I wanted to be in the CIA I said
yes and I was in I could you summarize
your experience in the cultural
terrorism at the CIA sure I joined the
cia's counter-terrorism center in
1998 specializing in something that's
it's quaint now uh it was a Greek uh
communist terrorism
which believe it or not was actually a
problem for us back in the day uh
but I spoke Arabic and my my bachelor's
degree was in Middle Eastern studies I
had a specialty in Islamic theology I
spoke Arabic fluently but I also speak
Greek fluently and as it turned out they
were looking for someone who spoke
either Greek or Arabic as it turned out
I was the only person in the entire CIA
who spoke both Greek and Arabic and so
they put me in counterterrorism I did
two years in Athens working not just
against Greek groups which no longer
exist but against the likes of Abu nidal
and the popular front for the liberation
of Palestine the Libyan intelligence
service the Iraqi intelligence service
things like that tell me how did the
Soviet Union's existence inform the
focus and priorities of the CIA during
this period
on my very first day at the CIA all the
new hires go into What's called the
bubble it's it's a large Auditorium just
outside the old headquarters building
and uh you get a briefing by the
director and the deputy director and the
head of security and the head of medical
the head of Finance everybody comes to
just tell you what they do and what to
expect in your CIA career and I will
never forget the director of security he
was a he was a tough old man at least in
my memory he was old
um and he looked at us all of us young
we were all in our early 20s and he says
the greatest threat facing the United
States today is the threat of Soviet
communism
well this was January 1990 the Berlin
Wall had just come down three weeks
earlier
and I remember thinking wow
can't believe I'm gonna work against
Soviet communism because it's kind of a
Jen's bone thing that's exactly what it
was it was a James Bond kind of thing
um no of course that turned out to be
ridiculous and he was living in the past
uh what it ended up becoming was a fight
against Global proliferation mostly of
nuclear weapons but also of chemical and
radiological
biological weapons
um but even he didn't realize that the
world had changed because it had just
changed like three weeks earlier so um
in the end my assignment was to work on
Iraq uh which I complained about because
nothing ever happened in Iraq ever it
was the same it was the same cabinet
since
1968. we would go sometimes an entire
day without receiving a single report on
Iraq from anywhere in the world and so I
complained I said listen I'm sitting
here like you know playing with myself
all day long I got to do something else
and my boss said you're brand new just
learn the writing style learn what we do
and then we'll put you on something more
interesting like Romania he said and I
thought oh okay Romania is interesting
they just killed Jose and you know
well nine months later just as I start
to feel like I know what I'm talking
about Iraq invades Kuwait
and one of the senior analysts pulled me
aside and said I don't think you realize
the importance of what just happened he
said it's not unusual for countries that
we covered to go to war with each other
it's very unusual for countries that we
cover to go to war with us
and so the very next day
I was sitting in the Oval Office with
the president the vice president the
Secretary of State the Secretary of
Defense the National Security adviser
and the director of the CIA and the
president said so tell me what I need to
know and everybody turns and looks at me
I was 24 years old
and I thought oh if my friends could see
this they wouldn't even believe it but I
realized now this is
like this yeah this is fun this is going
to work for me and so for the next
eight years it was all Iraq all the time
right would you say that you were a bit
naive before Oh yes yeah oh I was very
very naive not just when I joined the
CIA but through most of my CIA career I
was very naive you know in the 1990s
when Bill Clinton became president he
ordered the CIA to do something called a
cull c-u-l-l and what he meant was he
wanted the CIA to go through literally
every one of its files and if any
recruited Source had a problem in his
background with human rights he was to
be fired
and the CIA actually fired about a third
of their sources all around the world
and I remember thinking wow they're
really serious about human rights this
is great because I'm sorry
this is great because that was always an
issue that was important to me
um and that only lasted until September
11 2001. yeah
so that maybe that's the the perfect
moment to talk about Patriot Act
um so 9 11 arrived and maybe like a
month after say it was a month so so did
that tell me that was plan in advance
not 9 11 thing no I don't know about it
actually it wasn't planned in advance
and you know how you can tell it was so
badly written it was so broadly written
that individuals all across the country
had to begin filing lawsuits on the
grounds that was unconstitutionally
broad so what they did and they did the
same thing at the CIA they just said
we'll ask for everything
and we'll let the courts decide what we
can't have
well the courts decided that they could
actually have everything
everything you want NSA to spy on
Americans done you want NSA to intercept
every text message every phone call
every email of everybody in the United
States and hold it for 500 years done
here's an extra 10 billion dollars to
build the new facilities that you're
going to need you want to spy on
American peace groups go ahead do it
infiltrate them the FBI now is all over
the place
um
literally anything that the intelligence
Community or inner or national federal
law enforcement wanted they got it and
every once in a while thanks to Ed
Snowden who revealed this to us every
once in a while though there will be a
debate in Congress but so far the
Patriot Act has not been weakened it's
it's renewed year after year after year
don't forget that 9 11 was 18 years ago
so for 18 years we've been trying to get
our September 10th country back and
we've failed
John now I know that you've been talking
about that a lot but I'd love to know
how you ended up in prison
so in the immediate aftermath of the 9
11 attacks I was named chief of CIA
counter-terrorism operations in Pakistan
big job as you might imagine I had been
there for not long uh slightly less than
two months and we got word that Abu
zubaida was somewhere in Pakistan we
believed at the time that Abu zabeta was
the number three in Al Qaeda and so we
sought out to track him and it took us
six weeks but we found him
and we did we launched a series of raids
14 simultaneous raids on 14 separate
sites uh one night at two o'clock in the
morning and we caught him
so to make a very long story very short
when I returned to CIA headquarters
later in the spring I was asked if I
wanted to be
certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques I had never
heard that term before this was mid-may
2002.
so I said what does that mean enhanced
interrogation techniques and this
co-worker who had asked me
became very animated and he said we're
going to start getting rough with these
guys
I said what does that mean
and so he described these 10
techniques
I said that sounds like a torture
program he said no it's not torture we
got approval from the justice department
and the president said we could do it
and I said I don't know I think I have a
a moral problem with this give me an
hour to think about it
so I went I sought the the advice of a
senior officer a very senior officer for
whom I had worked in the Middle East
about a decade earlier
I said what do you think of this this
enhanced interrogation they just asked
me if I wanted to be trained in it
and he said
look let's call a spade a spade this is
a torture program they can call it
whatever they want they can use whatever
euphemism they want this is a torture
program and torture is a slippery slope
and you know how these guys are
somebody's going to go overboard and
they're going to kill a prisoner and
when that happens there's going to be a
congressional investigation and then
there's going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison do you want to go to prison I
said no I don't want to go to prison it
turned out I was the only person who
went to prison but I said no I don't
want to go to prison I went back
downstairs I said this is a torture
program and I don't want any part of it
and then that was May and then on the
1st of August 2002. they began torturing
Abu zubeda and other prisoners
um in the end they actually murdered two
prisoners that we know of there were
several other suicides that just don't
make any sense
um I just assumed that they were also
killed during interrogations
and I kept waiting for somebody to say
something but nobody said anything
so I left the CIA in the spring of 2004
and I went into the private sector and I
I put the CIA behind me
still waiting for somebody to say
something finally five and a half years
after that initial conversation in
December of 2007
a very important like nationally known
reporter for ABC News called me and said
that he had a source who said that I had
tortured Abu zubaida I said that was
absolutely untrue I was the only person
who was kind to Abu zubaida I said I
never laid a hand on him or any other
prisoner your source is either mistaken
or he's a liar
well he said and I didn't know this was
an old reporter's trick you're welcome
to come on the show and defend yourself
I said I'll think about it
in the next couple of days President
Bush gave a press conference this is
George W bush
and in that press conference he said
he looks right in the camera and he said
we do not torture
I knew that was a lie and I said to my
wife we were sitting on the couch
together watching this press conference
and I said he is looking the American
people in the eye and he's lying right
to our faces
and then a couple of days later he's
walking from the back of the White House
to the helicopter to go to Camp David
for the weekend and a reporter shouted a
question about torture and he turned and
he said well if there is torture it's
the result of a rogue CIA officer and I
turned to my wife and I said Brian
Ross's source is at the White House and
they're going to try to pin this on me I
said I'm going to go public
and so I called Brian Ross and I said
I'll give you your interview and I
decided that no matter what he asked me
I was just going to tell the truth I had
waited five and a half years for
somebody to say something nobody was
going to ever say anything and I thought
well I will and so I did
within 24 hours the FBI began
investigating me no surprise but a year
later in December of 2008 they sent my
attorneys what's called a declination
letter declining to prosecute me they
said I had not committed a crime
four weeks later Barack Obama becomes
president right hope and change right I
believe that lie too for a long time
I had no idea that the Obama
Administration asked the justice
department to secretly reopen the case
against me and so for the next three
years my phones were tapped my emails
were being intercepted and FBI agents
were following me everywhere I went and
finally in January of 2012 I was
arrested and charged with five felonies
including three counts of espionage
I hadn't committed Espionage having a
conversation with the New York Times or
with the ABC News is not espionage
um I was facing 45 years in prison it's
a death sentence
and finally the government offered me 10
years I said I'm not doing 10 minutes I
didn't do anything wrong they came back
a couple days later with eight years and
then two days after that five years and
my attorney my lead attorney I had 11
lawyers if you can imagine
all charging me 750 an hour
my lead attorney said sorry ah my
daughter they came down to five years
and I rejected it and my lead attorney
said you know I've been practicing law
here for 53 years and I've never seen
them come down in time
and I said why would they do that
because usually they'll offer you 10
years you say no they come back with 15
years if you say no to that then 20
years
but they kept coming down I said why
would they do that and he said because
they have a case and they know it's
he said we're going to trial
so that was our position for a very long
time finally
they came back with three and a half
years and we countered with one year
and they said no take the three and a
half or we're going for the whole 45.
and I said
I will testify on my own behalf at trial
and I may have to talk about some of the
Hideous crimes against humanity and war
crimes that I have witnessed in 15 years
in the CIA
so they came back and said all right two
and a half you do 23 months
I actually uh turned it down
crazy as it sounds now but this is a
commentary on the American judicial
system
this was best in final offer 23 months
and so my wife and I stayed up all night
long literally all night long talking
about it researching online because only
one other person had ever been charged
with this ever in the history of the
country and there was no case law
because she was an actual spy for a
foreign intelligence service
so I wrote to my lawyers at six o'clock
in the morning I said I decided to turn
it down
and an hour later two of them emailed me
and said we're on our way to your house
so two of them came over
and I said we were up all night we
discussed it we're going to turn it down
I said very foolishly as soon as I get
in front of a jury they're going to
realize how ridiculous this is I'm a
patriot I'm not a criminal
and then the lawyer that I liked and
respected the most pulled me aside
and said you know what your problem is
your problem is you think this is about
Justice and it's not about Justice it's
about mitigating damage take the deal
and I took the deal I asked him
realistically if I go to trial and I
lose what am I looking at and he said
realistically 12 to 18 years
so I took the deal the thing is one of
the techniques there are two techniques
that the government uses one is called
venue shopping where they will charge
you in the federal district where you
are most likely to be convicted and most
likely to receive the maximum sentence
that's the eastern district of Virginia
because it's right here and so and so a
jury would be made up of people from the
CIA the FBI the Pentagon intelligence
Community contractors you don't have a
prayer
the other thing is called charge
stacking which they also did to me let's
say they think they can get you on one
charge they'll charge you with 5 10 20
felonies they'll wait until you go
bankrupt and then they come back and say
all right if you take a plea to one
count we'll dismiss all the other
charges
so what do you do propublica came out
with a study in November 2012 in which
they found that the federal government
wins 98.2 percent of its cases almost
all of which are a result of plea
bargaining because of charge stacking
and venue shopping so if you know you
have a 1.8 percent chance of winning
do you roll the dice
and get 18 years I had five kids
so I took the deal
in jail food 23 months and because I
wrote those letters from Loretto they
didn't give me one single day off not a
single day everybody else is getting out
early six months in the halfway house
home confinement I sat in that cell for
every last day of the 23 months
do you think everyone in their own way
should be a whistleblower oh I think
everybody should be a whistleblower or
at least consider being a whistleblower
remember there's a legal definition of
whistleblowing it's bringing to light
any evidence of waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health or Public Safety the government
tells us all the time if you see
something say something there it is you
created a work and this desk is fascism
could you tell me a little bit the story
about yes that sure perfect peace I'll
start off by saying I'm the least
artistic person I've ever known I have
no artistic ability at all okay so
anyway I was in prison and
before I left for prison my attorney
told me that she had a very small
mailing list of 600 people who had
emailed her during the course of my case
saying that they wanted to know how I
was doing in prison so she said when you
get comfortable send me a letter I'll
type it and I'll send it to these 600
people
so I said okay I was there I got to
prison February 28th 2013.
and then the first week of May I felt
confident enough to sit down and write a
letter not really thinking that what I
was writing was I was exposing
wrongdoing on the part of the guards I
just thought all guards were I
didn't know they were actually breaking
the law by being so I wrote it
and I named their names too I sent it
out
to my lawyer and then a couple of nights
later
one of the guards came up to me and said
you're famous and not in a good way
and I said what's that supposed to mean
and she took me to the little guard
booth and she turned the computer around
and there I was my picture Banner
headline on The Huffington Post I didn't
know my lawyer was friends with Ariana
Huffington and so she sent Ariana the
the letter
that I called letter from Loretto and it
went crazy from there CNN Fox MSNBC uh
The Economist Playboy the Atlantic
Monthly I got more interview requests
than I could handle
and so I decided
I'm gonna make this a series
right the guards were so scared at the
Press reaction
I told the guard one time
don't with me unless you want to
see yourself on CNN tomorrow morning
and he backed off and I thought hey
I have a little bit of power here
so I called it letters from Loreto
because I wanted to emulate Martin
Luther King's letter from Birmingham
Jail and so I would do a letter whenever
one struck me whenever I saw something I
didn't like whenever I wanted to write
about a certain issue whether it was the
food or violence or whatever
in one of the guards committed suicide
near the end of my uh of my sentence I
wrote about that
uh and um
and they hated it and interestingly
enough they thought that I was smuggling
them out somehow one of the guards told
me that they had been talking about me
in the warden's office and they
concluded that I had a secret cell phone
hidden somewhere and I was dictating the
letters on the cell phone that's how I
got them out well the truth was I would
write them in plain view
I would put them in an envelope and put
them in the mailbox
that was it all they had to do was look
to look at the mailbox yeah so I wrote
something like 16 of them I think and
they became a book called doing time
like a spy which won a nice literary
award here one one of the big four
literary awards the pen First Amendment
award
but um to get to the artwork
they were Furious that I was writing
these letters and so
a friendly guard warned me they're going
to try to take your desk off the wall
and so I paid another prisoner a bag of
tuna fish
to strip the screws
and sure enough two hours later the
guards came with the drill and they're
trying to drill the desk off the wall
and it wouldn't come
so they finally walked away and I took a
legal pad and I wrote this desk kills
fascism and I stuck it to the desk and
then a couple of hours after that when
they were walking around to count the
prisoners that they do five seven times
a day I forget
he tore it off and crumpled it up and he
threw it at me which is really what I
wanted him to do then I flattened it out
and I mailed it back to myself and then
I
I took a couple of art classes I found
that I actually kind of had a knack for
it a little bit and and I made a screen
print of the of the page I made a
hundred copies
and I'm selling them to pay my attorneys
when were these Arenas first given
attention by the CIA and why were they
considered so important in the first
place yes the CIA became very interested
in art in the early 1950s and it was all
part of the the Cold War you know the
the battle between the superpowers uh
and and it's funny
the Russians we know that the Russians
were very worried about abstract art
because they thought that there were
messages embedded political commentaries
that were implied well the CIA was kind
of the same way they wanted there to be
embedded messages and political
commentaries they also respected the
Soviets use of uh realist art they call
it Soviet realism
and so uh the CIA began
I don't want to use the word targeting
maybe I will use the word targeting
artists who specialized in that uh genre
right the Cubans did it the Eastern
Europeans did it the Russians always did
it the Chinese came to do it a little
bit later in the decade
and so
you know the CIA thought that that was a
a great place to meet
Nationals of those countries maybe to
infiltrate that world
to um
to recruit sources
you know the Mantra at the CIA is that
our job is very simple it's to recruit
spies to steal secrets that's it that's
what we do recruit spies to steal
Secrets but you have to be inventive and
able to do that successfully
nobody's going to think to recruit an
artist
why would you well because artists have
access to very important people in
society
and so what better way to start yeah
yeah you you told me just before we we
start shooting uh that I never thought
of that but it's true during a cocktail
party this is the best way for just
talking it's the best way
a boss of mine in the counter-terrorism
center once paid me a great compliment
we were
I had been developing a very sensitive
Source it was he was so sensitive that
we couldn't meet in his country so every
time we needed to meet I would fly to
Europe somewhere and we would meet in a
hotel
and his information proved to be
perfect every time and so my boss said I
want to meet him
and so we flew out
to Central Europe and um
you know before you get down to business
you're sitting talking and we were
talking about art and theater and books
and film and whatever and afterwards my
boss said you know he said I've been a
CI officer for 30 years and I don't
think I've ever seen anybody
speak so in depth on so many different
issues as you did today
I said oh thank you I said you know I'm
actually interested in these issues I
like art and theater and film and books
and etc etc I like it it's not a job to
me it's fun
well that's how this Source was he was
he was very
um
wealthy and important and well connected
to the highest levels of people in his
government
and he liked me
and really that's the job the job is
to get you to believe that we are such
close friends you like me so much that
you're willing to commit treason for me
which is a death penalty offense but you
do it because you really really like me
what were the earliest intervention into
the wheels of art and culture that you
may be aware of
I'm aware
I am in the 1950s to cultivate artists
within what became known as the
Washington colorist school so
um the CIA actually began collecting art
from artists of the Washington color
School the Art today is worth millions
and millions of dollars and it hangs all
over the walls of the hallways of the
cia's new headquarters building
uh
but the people who created that art were
important Society figures in Washington
in the 1950s they all congregated in
Georgetown for example famously books
have been written about this
well who did they congregate with who
did they have dinner with those evenings
that they were talking about art the
Russian Ambassador the Chinese
Ambassador the French Ambassador
whatever visiting dignitaries happened
to be in famous International
businessmen or men of intrigue right you
know in the James Bond movies that James
always runs into the CIA officer that
happens every day in real life we always
see each other and we say hello
good to see you and then you go your way
and he goes his way well I mean we're
working the same parties and those
parties are full of artists and and
important Society figures especially in
the 1950s when the whole point was
communism
it seems that still with Russia it's
still a kind of fight right yeah but
it's different it's far less ideal
ideological now far less philosophical
yeah it's much more pragmatic yeah yeah
that's why neoliberals are so up in arms
about about Russia right now the
Russians are no threat to us no none
none whatsoever and there are a hundred
different ways that we should be
cooperating with the Russians terrorism
drugs proliferation poverty human rights
all different kinds of things but we
don't right because we need an enemy and
the Russians are the bad guys
that's just the way it's always been is
that amaze me
actually the CIA took its lead from from
the Soviet Union uh when they chose
abstract art as the vehicle uh to to
deliver the message and it was because
the Soviets were so worried by abstract
art they didn't understand it they
thought it was perverse in some way it
was somehow a threat to communist
ideology and the CIA thought that was
great that's a that's a a oh shoot I'm
having a mental blank hold on one second
let me think of what what was the word
we used to use that's good one
millimeter now abstract expressionism no
vulnerability so they loved that to them
that was a vulnerability within the
Soviet system and so they sought to
exploit it which is what they were paid
to do that was their job and the more
money that they put in the more they
believed they were succeeding and it
wasn't just abstract art back then too
it was also the translation of classic
Uh Russian literature there was
literature for for example Dostoyevsky
that was published well before the the
Bolshevik Revolution That Was Then
banned in the Soviet Union well the CIA
would translate it into Russian and then
smuggle it into the Soviet Union and
just they would hand it out for free it
was the same thing with art I mean you
can't hand the art out for free but you
can certainly hand out flyers and photos
and articles about the art in Russian or
Romanian or Bulgarian or whatever
and it was actually a successful
operation in that it got under the skin
of the of the Soviet government and they
had to react and respond to it why
abstract art because it promotes
individualism you took the word right
out of my mouth yeah abstract art is
about individualism not about
collectivism you know we're all familiar
with that Soviet art of the the perfect
handsome Russian soldier and the
beautiful Russian female Russian soldier
looking off into the sky with the hammer
and sickle over here and their rifles
yeah it's great everybody's seen it
everybody knows it
um but abstract expressionism was
confusing to them it was decadent it was
dangerous it was very American
and uh and they weren't sure how to uh
deal with it there's also a a a
historicism to the form of abstract art
there's so much it's almost a
deliberateness and it's lack of concrete
meaning in a way so true so true I I
worked for an ambassador in Bahrain for
two years and he was a great great fan
of abstract expressionism and he had
quite a large piece
um
installed in the in the official
residence we have a program here in the
United States called the Arden embassies
program and so through the state
Department's office of artistic Affairs
any Ambassador anywhere in the world can
request a piece of art from the
Smithsonian institution real art right
worth millions upon millions of dollars
this piece of art that he had was so
ugly that I I hated even to look at it
and for whatever reason he knew I
subscribed to art news magazine at the
time so he would always seat me at the
dining room table so that I had a view
of the art right in front of my face and
it was awful it was just these four
panels I'll never forget it painted gold
and then there was a red splotch down
here on the first one in the middle on
the second one at the top on the third
one and back at the bottom again and the
fourth one and it meant nothing to me
one night the uh the king came to dinner
right so we had this big bash it was two
dozen people and his Majesty's at one
side and the ambassadors at the other
side and we're all sitting there you
know afraid to
say anything and the Ambassador said how
do you like my my art it's abstract
expressionism
and the King said
David he said I hate it
I hate it he said it's ugly and it means
nothing to me now I had been looking at
this thing for two years it meant
nothing to me and he said no your
majesty he said it's the day
it's Sunrise midday evening and midnight
and I thought to myself how in the world
do you get that out of this ugly gold
and red
panel
but then you know after thinking about
it he was he was right now it was funny
to us that the king thought it was ugly
and the Ambassador thought it was great
but imagine being Joseph Stalin looking
at it and thinking there's a message in
there somewhere and I don't like it one
bit
and I know there's a message because the
Americans are putting this thing all
over the place
so it was an effective propaganda tool I
wonder if the CIA still uses cultural
propaganda the CIA doesn't have to use
cultural propaganda anymore uh Hollywood
does it for them and certainly there are
connections between the CIA and
Hollywood Studios there always have been
not just the CIA but also the FBI you
know there were no FBI shows on American
television that weren't made without the
cooperation of J Edgar Hoover's FBI and
so every show on American TV that
mentioned the FBI was a pro-fbi show
well the cia's office of public affairs
has a branch embedded within it here at
CIA headquarters whose job it is solely
to work with with Hollywood film studios
so every depiction of the CIA is a
positive depiction so you know these big
blockbuster movies that are made and
that go overseas that are frequently
banned in China for example they're all
cleared by the CIA look at the film Zero
Dark 30 for example this is kind of an
egregious example of this issue
Catherine Bigelow was the director and
producer Mark bull was the writer
they're both Academy Award winners very
important figures in Hollywood well they
wanted to do zero dark 30. zero dark 30
I thought was scandalous because it
perpetuated a lie and the lie was that
the torture program led to the location
of Osama bin Laden that was a lie the
torture program had nothing whatsoever
to do with the location of Osama bin
Laden really great analysis is what
caught Osama bin Laden
but Bigelow and bull were invited to
come to CIA headquarters where they were
treated to a classified briefing
that took place over a classified
mock-up of the bin Laden compound that's
a violation of the Espionage Act
after that was done and Bin Laden was
was killed they were invited back to
hear a speech by then CIA director Leon
Panetta in the bubble that I talked
about earlier that that big theater just
outside the original headquarters
building
in the speech Leon Panetta revealed
classified information
120 lines of classified information we
now know including the classified name
of the Navy SEAL who actually killed Bin
Laden
that's also a violation of the Espionage
Act but what did Catherine Bigelow and
Mark bull do they went back to Hollywood
they made this CIA propaganda film it
went all around the world it made
hundreds of millions of dollars at the
box office and now you have people
really believing that the cia's torture
program resulted in the capture of Osama
bin Laden that's what we need to be more
fearful of now it's not placing abstract
art and Museum shows around the world
it's this active propagandization of not
just the American people but the rest of
the world I've been told that yourself
to work for the CIA as an advisor right
for one year for one year yes could you
tell me about that uh I did it as I did
it on a lark so there was a there's an
employee database where they they post
notices like uh this section of the
parking lot is going to be closed for
repaving or this entrance is closed
because the president's coming or things
like that just normal administrative
things and one day there was a memo
saying that there is a vacancy on the
CIA art Advisory Board I didn't even
know there was a CIA art Advisory Board
although I did admire the art for you
know the six years previous that I had
been at the CIA and so
um I applied and I said I know a little
bit about art I have three Andy Warhols
as you can see around here and and I
have a Fernando botero and
you know they're not posters they're all
signed and numbered lithographs and such
I I love this stuff I've got some
prominent Greek artists um
art is important to me and uh and sure
enough I was appointed and I I thought
that it was going to be you know art
acquisition or conservation or whatever
and it wasn't we met four times and all
we ever discussed is what to hang where
uh they were in the process of of
building a new CIA Museum on the on the
first floor of the new headquarters
building and so we had to move the art
out of that area during construction and
put it in different halls and
it was underwhelming but it was
important to me that that there be art
at the CIA if you go to the White House
if you go like I said earlier to
American embassies around the world that
participate in the art and embassies
program there's world class art
and it's there for anybody who wants to
look at it and I thought the CIA should
have great art too
as the concept of soft power
yeah soft power is critically important
especially when you want to be the one
and only superpower in the world
um
you've heard the phrase
the carrot and the stick soft power
really is the carrot in a way
it's not a threat of of a bombing strike
or a drone attack or sanctions at the
United Nations it's the influence of
American culture it's the the
propagation of American ideas or ideals
just because we're bigger and stronger
and more popular than you are and so
it's become a very important part of
American foreign policy but especially
since the end of the Vietnam War and
it's because also the world has gotten
so much smaller with the internet and
streaming services for example it's much
easier for somebody in Siberia to log on
to Netflix for example and watch you
know American westerns or or for
somebody in Cuba to watch every season
of friends let's say well that has
propaganda value in that you come to
identify with the things that you're
watching you know there's kind of a
famous story
that in the late 1980s when there were
pro-democracy riots taking place in
Seoul South Korea the North Koreans
capitalized on this by by showing real
footage news footage of the
demonstrations on North Korean
television well North Koreans were
speechless when they saw it not because
there were demonstrations or riots they
couldn't believe how well-dressed
everybody was how well-fed they were
what beautiful cars they were driving
and it backfired on the North Koreans
that's kind of a reverse example of what
soft power is we can say look at our
great movies you know wouldn't you like
to be like us you can be like us you
just have to love us and respect us and
that actually works what was the concern
of the CIA when you left when I left it
was all about terrorism I'll give you
I'll give you a small anecdote in the
couple of weeks after the 9 11 attacks
everybody in the building had to drop
whatever he or she was doing and focus
on terrorism well I was already focused
on terrorism I was in the CIS
counterterrorism office and I had
um been recently promoted so I went up
to Ambassador Cofer black the head of
counterterrorism with an idea I said
kofer I have an idea for an operation I
want to pass by you he put up his hands
he said whatever it is just do it I have
so much money I can't possibly spend it
all
and that was it and that wasn't just me
because he liked me that was anybody
just do it everybody in the building was
coming up with ideas for operations
against terrorism is the CIA is still
actively involved today in promoting
works of art yes the CIA as an
organization is very involved in
promoting these kinds of works even
though they're not necessarily made by
the CIA this isn't some kind of a
clandestine program let's say to make a
movie or make a documentary and try to
get it distributed they don't waste
their time doing things like that they
have such good close relations with
Hollywood Studios I wonder what is the
ideology of the CIA the ideology is is
nationalism it's as simple as that
because if you are an American
nationalist let's say an American
exceptionalist everything else is going
to fall into line it's that easy do you
have any knowledge on how the Art Market
fits into the Global Financial system
I'm I'm told uh by by people with
first-hand experience whether it's at
the FBI or the treasury Department that
uh the only two ways that you can
launder money these days you know in in
this era of everything being
um electronically recorded is through
ART and real estate uh real estate's a
little bit tougher you set up an LLC
maybe the LLC is based in the Isle of
Man or in Liechtenstein or the Caymans
or whatever
but there's no record of who buys and
sells art anywhere and so there's no
record of whether or not art is bought
and sold with cash
a what art dealer what art gallerist
wouldn't want to sell a million dollar
piece even if it's in cash and then he
or she has to worry about how to launder
the cash that's what they do
and so this is a problem that I know
that the FBI has been facing for a long
time I had a conversation about this in
2002 or 2003 that they just couldn't get
a handle on transactions that were
taking place in the art community thank
you I have now some general questions
John do you think there is such a things
as truth and Justice in art
in the past I would have told you no
today I'm going to tell you yes and I'll
tell you why
um
so I've become acquainted with AI weiwei
the Chinese activist and artist what a
what a good and decent man this guy is
uh
six weeks before the end of my prison
sentence I started receiving these
postcards in the mail they were just
simple postcards blank on one side and
on the other side it was a photograph of
an eagle soaring through the air and on
the other side there might be a picture
drawn or a heart or you are not
forgotten or something most of them were
unsigned
and finally another prisoner came up to
me and said hey buddy you're in a
magazine uh it was the the week it's a
competitor of Time Magazine
I didn't know I was in this magazine but
it was an article about an exhibit that
way way had created that had been placed
at Alcatraz the notorious prison in San
Francisco Bay
and what he did was he
he took photographs of 189
political prisoners or prisoners of
conscience from around the world from 23
different countries and he made
portraits out of Legos
and the portraits appeared all over the
floor throughout Alcatraz and then in
individual cells especially in solitary
confinement there were other
installations ceramic flowers for
example thousands of ceramic flowers I
have one upstairs that he gave me
and um
the reason he did this was twofold one
when he was five years old his father
was arrested by Chinese authorities and
charged with Espionage for writing a
poem that one interpretation was
advocated democracy
so the entire family after his father
was arrested the entire family was
forced to move to far northeastern China
sort of the Chinese version of of
Siberia and he was interned in a camp
there
so one day someone sent him a postcard
and said you are not forgotten and it so
improved his morale that it led him to
begin writing poetry again even though
he was being held in this prison camp
and way way always said that his father
talked about it through his life about
what that postcard meant to him because
he really did think he was forgotten I
can tell you I you know
I always worried that I was forgotten
you know you're inside you're in prison
your life comes to a complete standstill
but the real world keeps moving on
outside
you know my best friend in prison
um his sentence was commuted by
President Obama and he was released but
he had been in for 17 years he had never
seen a cell phone before let alone an
ATM machine or use the internet or
anything
so you come to a stop the world keeps
moving and I ended up receiving
well over 2 000 of these postcards and
then the day that I got out of prison
was the last day of the exhibit and
weiwei's gallerist walked around with an
iPad and showed me the whole the whole
thing well that was 2015.
and we're still talking about it now at
the end of 2019 because
that exhibit went everywhere and it was
purchased by the Smithsonian institution
as crazy as it sounds are reports
portraits now are all hanging in the
Smithsonian institution in The
hirschhorn Gallery of Art
and there's a documentary that's been
made about the conceptualization and the
development and finally the installation
of this program uh the response from
Europe is far far greater than the
response from the United States
and I've always said this that the
Europeans are light years ahead of the
United States in terms of respect for
human rights and civil rights and civil
liberties and transparency not the Brits
the Brits are just like we are
but everybody else is far ahead and so
if I think outside the United States yes
I think truth and Justice and
transparency and freedom will eventually
Prevail it'll take us longer here